Finding Aid for John Richard Behee Sound Recordings, 1969-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Richard Behee sound recordings 1969-1974
Behee, John Richard.
95100 Aa 2
Historian of University of Michigan athletics, most notably football. Sound cassettes of interviews with African American athletes regarding their experiences at the University of Michigan.
29 audiocassettes
1 folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of John Behee (donor no. 4889 ).
The collection is open to research.
John Behee received his doctorate at the University of Michigan in 1970. He is the author of two books on University of Michigan athletic history: Fielding Yost's Legacy to the University of Michigan" (1970,) and Hail to Victors; Black Athletes at the University of Michigan (1974). Behee was a long-time professor at Tri-State College in Angola, Indiana.
The collection consists of audio cassettes and digital files of interviews with African American athletes regarding their experiences at the University of Michigan. Included is the proposal Behee wrote for the oral history project. The interviews were part of the Behee's research for his book Hail to the Victors.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Behee, John Richard.; African American athletes--Michigan.; Discrimination in sports.; University of Michigan--Sports.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Audio Recordings - Digital Files
  The oral history interviews conducted by John Behee between 1968 and 1974 cover a period from 1922 (William DeHart Hubbard) to 1972 (Godfrey Murray). They follow a fairly consistent pattern of questions and topics:
  motivation and circumstances that brought the athlete to Michigan
  high school experience and honors
  athletic experience / accomplishments at U-M
  relations with coaches and fellow players
  any particular experience of discrimination or prejudice, in particular with regard to lodging and travel
  any notable positive experience with coaches, teammates or others
  election of Blacks as team captains
  campus social life, including fraternities and interracial dating
  housing discrimination in Ann Arbor
  educational and work experience
  response to the Black Action Movement BAM and the larger civil rights movement.
  The interviews range from ca. 40-minutes to ca. 80 minutes in length. They are listed chronologically by date of the athletes U-M career. The sound level on some recordings is fairly low and you many need to raise the volume on your speaker.
  - William DeHart Hubbard; Track, 1922-1925, 1970 September 26, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Cleveland, Ohio by John Behee. William DeHart Hubbard, discusses his high school experience in Cincinnati and how he came to U-M, track accomplishments at U-M and at 1924 Olympics, setting world record in long jump, discusses failure to be elected team captain in 1925, black social life on campus.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-16-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-16-2]; mp3 file
  - Henry Graham; Tennis, 1928, 1970 September 26, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-14-1]; mp3 file; (Interviewed at his Cleveland home by John Behee. Henry Graham: Michigan’s first black varsity tennis player, discusses his decision to attend to U-M, making the varsity tennis squad, discrimination on team trips, housing discrimination in Ann Arbor, his educational experience, quota system in Medical School, social life for black students, reaction to BAM)
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-14-2]; mp3 file
  - Daniel Kean; Tennis, 1934, 1970 December 18, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Tape 1; Interviewed in Pittsburgh, PA by John Behee. Dan Kean, who pent two years at Fiske University in Nashville before coming to U-M, was invited to try out for the varsity tennis team by coach John Johnstone after winning a campus tournament, discusses his motivations for coming to U-M, family background, the African-American tennis circuit, other black Big Ten tennis players from the 1920s and 1930s. Talks about intramural basketball and the conference ban on black varsity basketball and generally on the nature of prejudice; discusses his perspectives on BAM and militant protest, relations with his tennis teammates and the taboo against discussion of race.)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-19-1]; mp3 file
  - Willis Ward; Football, 1932-1934; Track, 1933-1935, 1970 September 19, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Ward discusses his experiences after the University of Michigan, including the circumstances of his recruitment, relationship with coach Harry Kipke and Fielding Yost, the notorious 1934 Georgia Tech game controversy in which he was held out of the game at Tech's insistence, competing against Jesse Owens and failure to make the 1936 Olympic team, as well as his experiences in World War II and his career at the Ford Motor Company.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-27-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-27-2]; mp3 file
  - Willis Ward; Football, 1932-1934; Track, 1933-1935, 1970 September 19, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-28-1]; mp3 file; (Ward discusses his experiences and academic performance at the University and football experiences. Ward also discusses his perspectives on modern African-Americans.)
  - Joseph Hayden Jr.; Track, 1948, 1970 December 19, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (John Behee interviews Joseph Hayden Jr. in Detroit. Discusses decision to attend U-M, high school career at Alabama A&M Lab School, Normal AL, time in the military, decision not to play football at U-M, relations with tack coaches Ken Doherty and Don Canham, election of track captains, social life and interracial dating, prejudice against hiring back high school coaches in Detroit.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-15-1-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-15-2-1]; mp3 file; (John Behee interviews Joseph Hayden Jr. in Detroit.)
  - Julian W. Witherspoon; Track, 1944, 1945, 1970 November 28, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed by John Behee in Detroit. Witherspoon discusses his motivations to go to the University of Michigan, his family's encouragement, and his experiences at the University including dealing with discriminatory accommodations and a refusal to use a backdoor at a Chicago hotel, conflicts with faculty members over his outspoken attitudes.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-29-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-29-2]; mp3 file
  - Horace Coleman; Track, 1946, 1970 December 19, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Detroit by John Behee. Horace "Hap" Coleman came to U-M as a grad student with one year of eligibility after competing at Western Michigan. He played football but quit the team when it became clear that Coach Fritz Crisler would not give him much playing time. He won a varsity letter in track. Coleman discusses his high school experience as three sport athlete at Hamtramck, playing at Western, talks about Len Ford's first year at U-M, discusses his track experience at U-M and his work as educator and counselor.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-6-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-6-2]; mp3 file
  - Charles Fonville; Track 1946, 1947, 1948, & 1950, 1970 September 18, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed by John Behee in Detroit. Charles Fonville, a world record holder in the shot put and top Olympic prospect in1948 until sidelined by injury, discusses his motivations to attend college and experiences at the University of Michigan, including his relationship with coach Ken Doherty, problems with accommodations on the road and discrimination he faced at the 1948 Kansas Relays where he broke the word record.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-11-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-11-2]; mp3 file
  - Lowell Perry; Football, 1950, 1951, & 1952; Track, 1951, 1970 September 18, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Lowell Perry, an All-American Football end at Michigan. Lovell Perry discusses his high school career in Yspilanti and decision to attend U-M, black athletes at Michigan.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-23-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-23-2]; mp3 file
  - Tom Johnson; Football, 1949, 1950, 1951; Track: 1951 & 1952, 1970 September 19, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed at Ann Arbor by John Behee. Tom Johnson discusses his experiences attending the University of Michigan and his motivations and experiences at the University of Michigan, relationship with coach Jack Blott, changes in recruiting fo black athletes in the 1950s, influence of Martin Luther King.)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-18-1]; mp3 file
  - John E. Codwell Jr.; Basketball, 1952-1954, 1970 December 14, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed by John Behee in Detroit, Codwell discusses his decision to attend U-M and help break an informal "gentleman's agreement" among Big Ten basketball coaches barring black players until 1948. Comments on his athletic and educational experience, relations with coaches Bill Perigo and Dave Strack, discusses his positive reaction to the BAM, and his admiration of Martin Luther King's leadership.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-5-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-5-2]; mp3 file
  - G. Anderson White; Swimming (Diving), 1955, 1970 December 14, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Detroit by John Behee. G. Anderson White discusses his athletic and musical experiences in high school in Ferndale and the racism he experienced during his collegiate athletic career. He talks about coaches Matt Mann and Bruce Harlan, the difficulty in finding a place to train in metro Detroit in the summer, and being the first black to perform in the Michigan Union Opera, as well as his post-Michigan diving career in the military and competing in the 1956 Olympic trials. He comments on the social life)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-25-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-25-2]; mp3 file
  - Lovell Farris; Basketball, 1959-1960, 1970 December 23, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Detroit by John Behee. Lovell Farris discusses growing up in Batesville, Mississippi, and moving to Cleveland, Ohio, first person in family to attend college, decision to attend U-M, high school athletic career, relationship with coach Bill Perigo, discusses football players Willie Smith and Al Groce who were allegedly discriminated against because of interracial dating, housing discrimination in Ann Arbor, selection of M.C. Burton as first black basketball captain, educational experience at U-M, comments on lack of support services for minority student.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-10-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-10-2]; mp3 file
  - Richard A. Cephas; Track 1959-1961, 1970 December 23, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (John Behee interviews Richard A. Cephas: comments on his high school track experience, decision to come to Michigan, track accomplishments, Don Canham, experiences on team trip to Texas, social life and dating, his reaction to the BAM strike and university's response, his educational experience at U-M.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-4-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-4-2]; mp3 file
  - Marshall Dickerson; Track 1959-1961, 1970 November 28, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Detroit by John Behee. Marshall Dickerson, a high school teammate of Richard Cephas, discusses his motivations to attend U-M, recruitment by Don Canham, social life and academic experience at U-M, comments on importance of black consciousness in civil rights movement.)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-9-1]; mp3 file
  - Guy Curtis; Football, 1959-1961; Wrestling, 1960, 1962, 1970 September 19, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Detroit by John Behee about his motivations to attend college and his experiences at Michigan. Curtis was Michigan's first black wrestler and a Big Ten champion, as well as football player at the University of Michigan. Curtis describes his decision to come to Michigan, his high school experience in South Bend, Indiana, how he walked on to the football team and how Cliff Keen recruited him to the wrestling team, why there had been no black wrestlers at Michigan and few at other colleges, discrimination in housing in Ann Arbor, why he did not accept an athletic scholarship, how athletics aided his career in grad school and medical school; comments on BAM strike, but criticizes setting of 10% enrollment goal as a quota system.)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-8-1]; mp3 file
  - Ken Burnley; Track, 1961-1964; Assistant Track Coach 1968, 1970 October 26, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Ann Arbor by John Behee. Ken Burnley, varsity track in 1961-64. He became the first Black assistant coach at Michigan. He discusses his motivations and experience at Michigan, housing discrimination in Ann Arbor, his hiring as first black coach, support for the BAM strike.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-3-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-3-2]; mp3 file
  - Mike Willie; Football, 1963-1966 (did not letter), assistant trainer, 1972 April 24, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Ann Arbor, Mike Willie, a high school all-American halfback from New York City whose playing career was cut short by injuries, became an assistant trainer under Jim Hunt. He discusses his experiences at the University of Michigan, notable at 1965 trip to North Carolina where a KKK rally was held near the stadium the day before the game, and the challenges of living in Ann Arbor.)
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-26-1]; mp3 file
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-26-2]; mp3 file
  - Keith Cooley; Gymnastics (trampoline), 1966, 1970 August 27, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Keith Cooley was Michigan's first Black gymnast. Cooley discusses his motivations to go to Michigan and his experiences there, his relationship with coach Newt Loken, an effort to become football cheerleader, his experience in the engineering school, and reactions to the BAM and the university's response.)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-7-1]; mp3 file
  - Ronald A. Johnson; Football, 1966, 1967 & 1968, 1971 March 24, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-17-1]; mp3 file; (Interviewed in Ann Arbor by John Behee. Ron Johnson discusses his early life and family life in Detroit, his motivations in coming to U-M, athletic experience, being elected first black football captain, fraternities and social life.)
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-17-2]; mp3 file
  - Hail to the Victors by John Behee: Tom Goss, C.D. Henry; Dave Voight - NASSH "Politics & Sport", 1974 May 03,, 1972 May 08, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-13-1]; mp3 file; (Behee interviews Tom Goss, football player who later became U-M Athletic Director; discusses Big 10 rule changes on course content and athletes' progress toward a degree and African-Americans in sports in the Big 10. Phone interview with C.D. Henry about Affirmative Action in the Big 10.)
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-13-2]; mp3 file; (North American Society for Sport History lecture by Dave Voight. "Side 2 is not a part of the Michigan Black Lettermen Study" - John Behee. )
  - Ken Maxey; Basketball, 1967, 1968, & 1969, 1971 March 25, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-21-1]; mp3 file; (Interviewed in Ann Arbor by John Behee. Ken Maxey was 1969 basketball team captain. He discusses adjustment from all-black high school to mostly white university, relations with coaches and teammates, academic experience.)
  - Morris Abraham; Football, 1968-1969, 1969 February, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1], [95100-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Morris Abraham is interviewed discussing his experiences playing football and baseball in High School (Ann Arbor Pioneer), racism he experienced both in sports and outside of sports.)
    - [Side 2], [95100-SR-1-2]; mp3 file; (Morris Abraham is interviewed discussing his experiences in fraternities, other Black athletes he knew, and his academic performances.)
  - Morris Abraham; Football, 1968-1969, 1971 March 23, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-2-1]; mp3 file; (Interview content begins at about 1:30. Abraham discusses his most poignant athletic experiences.)
  - Rodney (Rod) Ford; Basketball 1969-1971, 1972 April 24, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-12-1]; mp3 file; (Interviewed by John Behee in Detroit. Ford discusses his family and experiences which motivated him to attend college, decision to attend U-M and study engineering, black fraternities/sororities and social life, hiring of coach assistant coach Richard Carter, comments of BAM.)
  - Jesse Rawls; Wrestling, 1969-1970, 1971 March 24, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips; (Interviewed in Ann Arbor by John Behee. Rawls discusses growing up in Guyton Georgia and moving to Harrisburg, PA at age seventeen. his high school athletic experiences and the motivation and circumstances that got him to Trinidad Junior College in Colorado and to Michigan, his relationship with coach Cliff Keen and wrestling experience at U-M., reasons for so few black wrestlers at collegiate levels, relations with is teammates, comments on bias keeping Jim Betts from playing quarterback, the role of back coaches, cites Nat Turner as a hero as well as Martin Luther King.)
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-24-1]; mp3 file
  - Godfrey Murray; Track, 1970-?, 1971 March 24, Audio Cassette, Compact Cassette, 1 7/8 ips
    - [Side 1; no Side 2], [95100-SR-22-1]; mp3 file; (Interviewed in Ann Arbor by John Behee. Godfrey Murray, from Kingston Jamaica at the time a sophomore track athlete at Michigan, discusses his experiences at Michigan, his selection as captain, social life and fraternities.)
- Audio Recordings - Cassettes
  - Original cassettes of Oral history interview (Box 1)
    [Staff use only]
  - Proposal for oral interview project (Box 1)